Guide to the Oral Histories Documenting Yale University Women
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Wasserman, Elga, 2007 May 24; Accession 2012-A-056
  Elga Ruth Wasserman was born Elga Steinherz in 1925 into a middle class Jewish family, in Berlin, Germany. She came to the United States at the age of twelve with her parents and younger brother to escape Hitler, and the family settled in Great Neck, Long Island. She excelled in high school, and won a scholarship to Smith College, from which she graduated with a B.A. summa cum laude in 1945. She considered a medical career but, for financial and personal reasons, she opted instead to do a Ph.D. in Chemistry at Radcliffe College, supervised by Nobel Prize winner Robert Burns Woodward. She graduated in 1948. She was, almost certainly, Woodward's one and only female doctoral student. She married fellow Woodward student, Harry Wasserman, in 1947. The Wassermans moved to Yale in 1948 when Harry Wasserman joined the Chemistry department as an instructor. She found a position at Yale as a research assistant in Microbiology but resigned voluntarily shortly before the birth of her first child. For the next twelve years she raised three children, supplementing the family income with part-time jobs as a chemist in industry and teaching at local community colleges. Once her third child was in school, she returned briefly in 1960-1961 to chemistry research at Yale, but in 1962 she accepted the position of assistant to the Dean of Yale Graduate School. She discovered that administration enabled her to be both professionally independent and to work part-time, so in 1964 she accepted the position of Assistant Dean at the Graduate School, with special responsibility for graduate science programs, a post she held until February 1969. Yale's decision in the fall of 1968 to admit women undergraduates led President Kingman Brewster to seek out Dr. Wasserman to oversee the implementation of co-education at the University. She was appointed chair of the University Committee on Coeducation before becoming Brewster's Special Assistant on the Education of Women, a post she held from 1969 to 1973, by which time Yale's transition to coeducation was complete. She felt it was then time to move on. Her experience with equal access issues at Yale resulted in Women in Academia: Evolving Policies toward Equal Opportunities, published by Praeger in 1975, and inspired her to become a lawyer. She graduated from Yale Law School in 1976. She spent the next twenty years, until her retirement, in private practice, first as a tax lawyer but subsequently as a family lawyer.
  In retirement, reflecting on her own experience as a scientist and administrator, Elga Wasserman began to address the question of why there are not more women in science. Her conclusions were published as Door in the Dream: Conversations with Eminent Women in Science (Joseph Henry Press, 2000), and she continues to write and speak on women in science and related issues.
  Elga Wasserman briefly recalls her early childhood in Nazi Germany and her first impressions of the United States. She reflects about the educational and social expectations of women in her family and in society at large in postwar America, speaking at some length about the ambivalences she encountered in college and graduate school towards women in higher education, especially in science. Throughout the interview she engages with the reasons why, in her view, women were, and continue to be, at a disadvantage in academic life, and the ways in which equity balance in academia might be achieved. She discusses the relationship between individual choices and structural change, and addresses tenure, salary, promotion and retention, and reflects on the significance of affirmative action and the opportunities it presented to women in the 1970s. She speculates at some length on why combining a professional career with motherhood appears, in her view, to be more difficult in the United States than other parts of the world.
  The bulk of Wasserman's interview deals with her career at Yale, including her experience as an Assistant Dean in the Graduate School, her work on the Coeducation Committee and her role as Special Assistant on the Education of Women to President Kingman Brewster. She talks at length about the reasons why she choose to work part-time when her children were small, and recalls the challenges faced by women scientists like Mary Ingraham Bunting (who she knew as a colleague at Yale) who combined full-time scientific research with motherhood. She talks about the difficulties she experienced as a faculty wife within the prevailing culture at Yale in the 1950s and the persistence of gender discrimination at Yale institutions like the Yale Club of New York and Mory's until the 1970s. She also recalls her relationships with senior Yale figures including John Perry Miller, John Wilkinson, Georges May, Henry "Sam" Chauncey, Jr., George Pierson, Alfred Fitt, Hannah Gray, Bart Giamatti and Kingman Brewster. Lastly, she devotes much time to the challenges and difficulties she experienced in her job overseeing coeducation and negotiating affirmative action within the university, and details the reasons she decided in the end to leave Yale to pursue a new career in the law.
  - Audiorecording, 172; ; 2 hours and 50 minutes
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Wynne, Marjorie G., 2007 November 12; Accession 2012-A-057
  Marjorie G. Wynne was born March 7, 1917, in Petersburg, Virginia. Her father died in the influenza pandemic of 1918, which obliged her mother to seek work as a secretary and eventually to open a nursery school and kindergarten. Despite the financial struggle, acerbated by the Great Depression, it was always assumed that Wynne would go to college. She graduated from Duke University in 1938 but, for financial reasons, did not consider graduate school. Instead, she worked for two years in the Duke Library to save enough money to go to library school, which she attended at the University at California, Berkeley, graduating with a Certificate in Librarianship in 1941. Remaining for a Master's degree was a financial impossibility. Instead, she worked briefly at the Pennsylvania Military College in Chester, Pennsylvania, before joining the staff of the Sterling Memorial Library at Yale University in 1942, initially as Serial Cataloguer and then Assistant in the Rare Book Room. From 1947 to 1963 she was Librarian of the Rare Book Room. With the opening of the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library in 1963, she was appointed as the Edwin J. Beinecke Research Librarian, a position she held until her retirement in 1987. In 1968 she became one of the first non-faculty women to be elected a fellow of Timothy Dwight College.
  Wynne has written many articles on bibliography, including a contribution to Rare Book Collections: Some Theoretical and Practical Suggestions for Use by Librarians and Students (American Library Association, 1965) and a guide to the J.M. Barrie collection in the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. She curated several exhibitions at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library and her published exhibition catalogs include James Joyce, 1882-1942 (1982) and F.T. Marinetti and Futurism (1983).
  After retiring, Wynne remained active in her discipline and is a member of the Grolier Club, the Association Internationale de Bibliophilie, and Yale's Elizabethan Club. She was one of the first women to be admitted to the Grolier Club in 1976 when it was opened to women for the first time. She has served as Secretary of the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences and as President of the New Haven branch of the English-Speaking Union. Her portrait, commissioned by the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library and painted by Irene Hecht, was unveiled in 2006. In the same year, she established the Marjorie G. Wynne fellowship in British Literature, which provides funds for visiting scholars at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
  Marjorie G. Wynne, who spent 45 years as a rare book librarian at Yale University, died on Sunday evening, April 5, 2009, in her home at Whitney Center in Hamden, Conn. She was 92 years old.
  Marjorie G. Wynne discusses her southern upbringing during the Great Depression and how this affected her subsequent life decisions. She recalls briefly her undergraduate education at Duke University and speaks extensively about her professional training and social life at the University of California, Berkeley, Library School and the support and encouragement she received from people like Edith Coulter and Richard Archer. The bulk of her interview is concerned with her long career at Yale University. She recalls her first impressions of the Sterling Memorial Library and why she chose Yale over a better paid position at Brown University. She reflects at length on her work as Librarian of the Rare Book Room. She recalls the library as one of the few places at Yale where women were highly visible, and discusses both the opportunities and limitations that women of her generation encountered there. She talks about several of the senior women, including Emily Hall and Grace Fuller, and their roles in the day-to-day operation of the library. She provides many personal anecdotes about University Librarians, James Tinkham Babb and Bernhard Knollenberg, and Chauncey Brewster Tinker, Librarian of the Rare Books Room. She also discusses relationships between library staff and faculty and her own involvement with the Yale Dramatic Association and Timothy Dwight College. Wynne recalls the building of the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library and the circumstances surrounding her appointment as the Edwin J. Beinecke Research Librarian. She talks about her encounters with Edwin Beinecke and her enduring friendship with Donald Gallup, the book collector and bibliographer. Her interview ends with discussion of her major retirement project (which was the refurbishment of the Elizabethan Club in 1996), her continuing involvement in rare book librarianship, and the painting of her portrait for the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library in 2006.
  - Audiorecording, 4; ; 2 hours and 47 minutes
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)